

Shaleen Munuhe

Date of birth: 03/10/1993 | **Nationality:** Kenyan | (+254) 0728535873 |

munuheshaleen@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/shaleenwangui |

P.O Box 69777 - 00400 Nairobi, Murera, Ruiru - Kiambu County., Kenya

About me:

Shaleen Munuhe is a renewable energy, energy efficiency, policy and advocacy expert. She is currently working as an independent consultant providing information and support to Off grid Companies (Solar Home Systems, Productive Use Solar and Solar Water Heating Companies) in the areas of policies and regulations and strategic issues such as opportunities and partnerships nationally and at county level. In addition to that, she is the East Africa Programme Consultant for Ashden International Skills Award Program sponsored by Linked In. The award aims to uncover and boost innovation in training in the energy access sector that could be repeated or replicated around the world. Prior to that, she was the Assistant Country Manager, Kenya, Somalia and Ghana at Tetra Tech International Development for the Africa Clean Energy Technical Assistance Facility, a 4-year programme funded by the UK Government Foreign, Commonwealth and Development Office (FCDO), aimed at catalyzing a market-based approach for private sector delivery of renewable energy electrification technologies, with a focus on high quality stand-alone solar systems. She has a vast professional experience in the private and public sector. She provides technical support in matters relating to advocacy, project design to renewable energy stakeholders and companies. Her work involves the development of feasibility studies, technical analysis, planning and design of projects, particularly in the stand-alone solar sub sector. She has conducted over twenty stakeholder workshops in the renewable energy field for multiple audiences including off grid companies, private sector, government officials and research and testing centers officials. She has extensive knowledge in utilizing renewable energy technologies for climate change adaptation and mitigation for economic growth in developing countries.

WORK EXPERIENCE

15/03/2022 - CURRENT - Nairobi, Kenya

EAST AFRICA PROGRAMME CONSULTANT - ASHDEN

- Conducting research and identifying potential applicants for international award themes. Helped to uncover and boost innovations in training in the energy access sector that could be repeated or replicated around the world.
- Identifying potential judges and knowledge partners for the award themes.
- Encouraging potential applicants and assist them to apply.
- $\circ\,$ Reading applications and assist in the selection of the longlist for the 2022 international awards.
- Conducting assessments of some longlisted and shortlisted applicants and present them to the
 judging panels. Conducted assessment for agricultural sustainable climate solutions in rural Kenya
 aimed at reducing farm losses. In addition to that, I conducted assessment for energy assess
 initiatives at Kakuma Refugee Camp.
- $^\circ$ Worked with Natural Based Solutions applicants in the Amazon rainforest and the Congo basin during the longlisting and shortlisting process
- Using insights and knowledge gained through the awards process to produce reports for use by the wider Ashden team.

Renewable Energy, Off Grid Energy Access | Electricity, gas, steam and air conditioning supply |

https://ashden.org/ | Nairobi, Kenya

31/07/2021 - CURRENT - Nairobi, Kenya

INDEPENDENT CONSULTANT - ADVISORY

Providing information and support to Off grid Companies(Solar Home Systems, Productive Use Solar and Solar Water Heating Companies)in the areas of policies and regulations and strategic issues such as opportunities and partnerships nationally and at county level.

Renewable Energy, Off Grid Energy Access

30/11/2020 - 21/07/2021 - Nairobi, Kenya

ASSISTANT COUNTRY MANAGER KENYA, SOMALIA AND GHANA - AFRICA CLEAN ENERGY TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE FACILITY(ACE TAF) – TETRA TECH INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT

- Coordinated technical experts working on the Economic Impact Assessment which is an economic and social analysis of the adverse effects Value Added Tax(VAT) and Import Duty on Off grid companies, which has played a significant role in the successful lobby for the reinstatement of VAT exemptions on solar products in the Kenyan Finance Bill 2021.
- Evaluated over 20 respondents from Kenya Revenue Authority (KRA), Solar PV companies and the Ministry of Energy and developed a report that acted as a guide for the proceeding activities and requirements necessary for the development of a revised Solar PV Importation Guideline 2021.
- Conducted meetings with Kenya Bureau of Standards and CLASP for the development of a code of practice which would be a guide for the development, maintenance, and installation of Stand Alone Solar(SAS) systems in Kenya. The project has however stalled due to budget cuts from the FCDO.
- Participated in the recruitment of experts working on the Somalia rural electrification Strategy.
- Coordinated meetings with the Somalia coordinator to ensure that the key stakeholders were well informed of Africa Clean Energy Technical Assistance Facility activities
- Edited market assessments for Kenya, Somalia and Ghana covering the impacts of the policies in the solar sector, impacts of COVID on businesses and fiscal barriers and incentives.
- Collaboratively worked with the country managers and assistant country managers in Nigeria, Sierra Leone, Senegal, Ethiopia, Uganda, Tanzania, Rwanda, Zambia, Malawi, Mozambique and Zimbabwe to develop market assessments covering the impacts of the policies in the solar sector, impacts of COVID on businesses and fiscal barriers and incentives in the respective countries.
- Development of publication materials such as articles on impacts of off grid solar on marginalized communities. These articles have often appeared in the newspapers such as the Business Daily.
- Coordinated work and meetings with the Ministry of Energy and other government authorities.
- Supported the collaboration across stakeholders in the off grid solar sector such as the Ministry of Energy, Kenya Renewable Energy Association(KEREA) and donors to avoid duplication of development activities.
- Drafted reports on key program activities, problems and action points for Kenya and Somalia.

Renewable Energy Program Management | Electricity, gas, steam and air conditioning supply

08/07/2018 - 29/11/2020 - Nairobi, Kenya

ADMINISTRATOR - KENYA RENEWABLE ENERGY ASSOCIATION

- Projected development of feasibility studies, technical analysis, planning and design of projects, particularly in renewable energy. My focus areas include; Advocacy projects focused on creating an enabling environment for business, organization of National Renewable Energy Conferences and Exhibitions and organization of Regional Workshops
- Organized Public Private Stakeholder Dialogues with National Assembly Committee on Energy, Environment, Trade and Finance, Kenya Revenue Authority(KRA), Energy Petroleum Regulatory Authority(EPRA), Kenya Bureau of Standards(KEBS) and the Ministry of Energy.
- Edited of the 5th Edition Energy Digest magazine, which an annual issue of a regional renewable energy magazine focusing on sectors in the renewable energy sector.
- Supervised the development of the East African Solar Taxation Handbook 2020 and the Solar PV Importation Guideline 2019 which outline the importation process for Solar products in East Africa and Kenya respectively.
- Biweekly newsletters creator and editor In charge of creating the Kenya Renewable Energy Association(KEREA) newsletter with up-to-date activities.
- Private sector representative at the BEAR 11, National Technical Committee, a TVET program sponsored by the KOREAN Government and UNESCO.
- Pitched to stakeholders, potential Investors or collaborations such BFZ, Africa Clean Energy Technical Assistance (ACE TAF) on KEREA's ongoing and upcoming activities
- Kenya Renewable Energy Association (KEREA) representative to the East African Renewable Energy Federation which is an organization that represents the interest of the East African Renewable Energy Associations to the EAC legislation.

- Developed a lobby group with representatives from GOGLA, Africa Mini-grid Developers
 Association(AMDA) and Clean Cooking Association of Kenya(CCAK) to advocate for the reinstatement
 of VAT exemptions on solar items. The lobby group later advanced to include partners such as Africa
 n Clean Energy Technical Assistance Facility(ACE-TAF), Power Africa, Africa Enterprise Challenge
 Fund(AECF), SNV and Green Mini Grid(GMG) Facility and formed a great networking platform for
 major stakeholders in the renewable energy sector.
- Coordinated of a legal expert working for Kenya Renewable Energy Association on the development
 of a legislative position paper to be submitted to the parliamentary advisory team for consideration
 in the Kenyan Finance Bill 2021 which led to the successful lobby for reinstatement of VAT
 exemptions on off grid products.
- Prepared proposals to developing partners as a form of raising funds to KEREA operations. Some of the developing partners included BFZ, SNV, UNDP and the African Clean Energy Technical Assistance Facility(ACE-TAF) program.
- Implemented projects to Improve Organizational Development and Services Offered to Members supported by German Federal Ministry for Economic Cooperation and Development via SEOUA.
- Membership recruitment and Retention.

Renewable Energy | Electricity, gas, steam and air conditioning supply |

3rd floor, Strathmore Business School, Keri Rd, Off Ole Sangale Rd., P.O. Box 42040-00100, Nairobi, Kenya., 00100, Nairobi, Kenya

04/08/2016 - 02/07/2018 - Nairobi, Kenya

PROJECT ASSISTANT - EAST AFRICAN DATA HANDLERS

- Streamlined an easy communication link with our partner Inter Switch, whose responsibility is to facilitate withdrawal of funds from our customers' Lipa na Mpesa accounts through their bank ATMs.
- Introduction of SAP software system as CRM system to ensure customer enquiries highlighted are completed. This ultimately led of the growth of the Go-Pesa till and pay bills from less than 100 to over 15000.
- Pioneered the partnership between Uwezo Microfinance Bank and Go-Pesa to allow our customers
 access loans through Uwezo Microfinance Bank. I conducted trainings and follow-ups for the Uwezo
 Microfinance sales representatives who were able sign in approximately three quarters of Uwezo
 Microfinance clients with our Lipa na Mpesa.
- Prepared a daily performance report on the daily transactions and the arising customer issues stating the commentaries to assist in decision-making.
- Trained and recruited new employees joining the Go-Pesa team.
- Monitored daily customers' transactions, ensuring that they reflect the correct balances and all the relevant account reconciliations are performed, and corrective actions taken.
- Batch proofed transactions done daily.

Fintech | Information and communication

27/09/2015 - 07/04/2016 - Nairobi, Kenya

TALENT ORGANIZATION AND DEVELOPMENT INTERN - RAFIKI MICROFINANCE BANK

- Introduced a new filling system for employee records whereby all employees' information details was kept in softcopy
- Calculated employee and employer payroll taxes using oracle application software, based on the bonuses, commissions and deductions for employee paid benefits. This was to ensure that the paycheck was current
- Ensured proper documentation of staff documents for filing purposes.
- Prepared of Certificate of Service for exiting staff.
- Participated by taking minutes for the Disciplinary Committee meetings, headed by the Head of Talent, Organization and Development.
- Prepared On-boarding documents for new staff, which consist of employee's personal information details.
- Ensured proper maintenance and use of office equipment that is for example furniture in the office.

SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT INTERN - MINISTRY OF LABOUR, SOCIAL SECURITY AND SERVICES

- Registration of Groups such as Women groups, Community Groups and Welfare Groups.
- Conflicts resolution among registered groups.
- Handling customer care desk.
- Visiting registered groups to assess their progress and informing them about the available government funds.
- Collecting data and carrying out needs assessment of older persons and people with disabilities.

03/07/2014 - 29/07/2014 - Nairobi, Kenya

RESEARCH CONSULTANT - IPSOS SYNOVATE

Information Gathering, Preparation of Questionnaires to the public through sampling method, drafting detailed report for presentation and publication

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

09/09/2012 – 01/12/2016 – University Way, Nairobi, P.O.Box 30197, GPO, Nairobi, Kenya, Nairobi, Kenya **BACHELOR OF ARTS IN ECONOMICS AND SOCIOLOGY –** University of Nairobi

https://www.uonbi.ac.ke/about-us

05/01/2014 - 29/11/2015 - Starehe, Guilders Centre, Moi Ave, Nairobi, Kenya

CPA PART 2 - Pinnacle Business School

09/01/2011 - 07/08/2011 - Harambee Shepherds Building, Kenya

DIPLOMA IN COMPUTER STUDIES - Unity School of Professional Studies

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Mother tongue(s): KIKUYU

Other language(s):

	UNDERSTANDING		SPEAKING		WRITING
	Listening	Reading	Spoken production	Spoken interaction	
ENGLISH	C2	C2	C2	C2	C2
SWAHILI	C2	C2	C2	C2	C2

Levels: A1 and A2: Basic user; B1 and B2: Independent user; C1 and C2: Proficient user

DIGITAL SKILLS

My Digital Skills

Microsoft Office | Microsoft Word | Microsoft Excel | Microsoft Powerpoint | Social Media | Zoom | Google Drive | Google Docs | Facebook | Power Point | Outlook | Team-work oriented | LinkedIn | Motivated | Skype | Internet user | Presenting | Creativity | Flexibility | Good time management | Responsibility | leadership | Gmail | positive thinking | Research | Presentation and negotiation skills | Efficient multi-tasking | Empathic listener

Interpersonal Skills

Good Communication | Good listener and communicator | Written and Verbal skills | Decision-making | Excellent writing and verbal communication skills

Project Skills

Strategic Planning | Reliability | Analytical skills | Detail-Oriented | Ability to Work Under Pressure | Re search and analytical skills | Teamwork | Critical thinking | Organizational and planning skills | Excellen t organizational planning and solving problems in short time | Good at being proactive and efficient in high stress situations

VOLUNTEERING

03/12/2016 - CURRENT

Community Work with Voluntary Counselors Kenya(VCK) conceived in 2003 whose main aim is mentoring, career guidance, creating constitutionalism awareness and economically empowering girls in semi urban areas.

Maasai Land

Community Work with Voluntary Counselors Kenya(VOK) conceived in 2003 whose main aim is mentoring, career guidance, creating constitutionalism awareness and economically empowering girls in semi urban areas.

31/12/2016 - CURRENT

Mentorship program with God's Idea (a youth group in PCEA Dandora Church). I am the secretary of God's Idea youth group meant to mentor teenagers in high school and youths in colleges

PCEA Dandora Church

Mentorship program with God's Idea (a youth group in PCEA Dandora Church). I am the secretary of God's Idea youth group meant to mentor teenagers in high school and youths in colleges

CONFERENCES AND SEMINARS

01/03/2020 - 05/03/2020 - Mombasa

Market Positioning Training

Market Positioning Training for Renewable Energy Associations and Businesses organized by German Federal Ministry for Economic Cooperation and Development via SEQUA

16/03/2019 - 23/03/2019 - Arusha

Fundraising and Proposal Writing Training

Fundraising and Proposal Writing Training for Non-Governmental Organizations organized by the East Africa Renewable Energy Federation

PUBLICATIONS

Evaluation of the Solar PV Importation Guideline

Shaleen / Mary Githinji

2021

The report was an evaluation of the Solar PV Importation Guideline 2019. The report will help guide the development of a revised version of the guideline to be undertaken by Kenya Renewable Energy Association

Economic Impact Assessment

https://www.ace-taf.org/kb/economic-impact-assessment-on-removal-of-tax-exemptions-on-stand-alone-s 2021

The report presents an assessment of the impact of VAT and import duties on household access to SAS products in Kenya, over the next five years.

https://www.ace-taf.org/kb/economic-impact-assessment-on-removal-of-tax-exemptions-on-stand-alone-solar-products-in-kenya-technical-report/

5th Edition Energy Digest

2020

The Energy Digest is an annual magazine that is focused on displaying the Renewable Energy technologies and opportunities available in Kenya.

I was a co-editor in this edition bringing out renewable energy opportunities in Kenya.

East African Solar Taxation Handbook

2020

The publication sort to clarify on the importation process for solar products in the East African region. I was the co author of this publication which was distributed regionally

RECOMMENDATIONS

Recommendations to be provided upon request